Guide to the Stanford Technology Ventures Program, Entrepreneurial Thought Leaders Seminar, Videorecordings SC1209
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Videorecordings, 2001-2014
  - Hawkins, Jeff, An Entrepreneur's Take on the Non-Profit, 2009-05-13; 2249; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Launching a non-profit organization is just as much work as starting a for-profit business, says Numenta Founder Hawkins, Jeff. Many of the issues and struggles of leadership are the same, including concerns about funding, building, mission statements, staffing, etc. Hawkins recalls that the Redwood Neuroscience Institute, focused on neocortical theory in the field of neuroscience, was so successful that they were forced to think of their next steps after just three years in operation. A friend showed him how to plot the institute's theories into mathematical planning software, and Numenta, a for-profit entity, was born.
  - Hawkins, Jeff, Effective Choices, Not Longer Days, 2009-05-13; 2250; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Throughout his thirty-year career launching four start-up organizations (including founding Numenta), Hawkins, Jeff has always sworn that the would be home for breakfast and dinner with his family every day. In this clip, Hawkins dispels the myth that launching an organization requires long office hours and frequent travel. Entrepreneurs, he says, can be effective without having to work hard. They do, however, have to make the right choices. Any organization that focuses on making better daily decisions will have the opportunity for broad and deep success.
  - Hawkins, Jeff, Forgo the NDA: Find Support Where You Can, 2009-05-13; 2251; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Hawkins, Jeff, Founder of Numenta, encourages entrepreneurs to involve people in their problems and to solicit as many qualified opinions as they can. Don't get tangled in product secrecy and idea ownership at the expense of gaining quality feedback. Instead, he says, be happy that anyone is willing to listen to your ideas and offer the benefit of their expertise. And when it comes to investors, have them involved as much as possible so that they, too, can share the weight of the worry.
  - Hawkins, Jeff, Case Studies of Failure, 2009-05-13; 2252; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    After designing about a dozen computer products, Numenta's Hawkins, Jeff recalls that two - among them the Palm Pilot - were very successful, half were good, and the remaining were market failures. Here, Hawkins discusses his thinking behind some of his product flops. He also tells the story of a fulfillment disaster that occurred with the launch of the Handspring Visor. After the online ordering system failed, every one of the product's tens of thousands of customers had to be called individually and asked if they'd received their order.
  - Hawkins, Jeff, Palm's Approach to Elegant Design, 2009-05-13; 2253; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Despite Microsoft's desire to crush the fledgeling Palm Pilot in the 1990's, Hawkins, Jeff, Palm's former Co-founder and now the Founder of Numenta, decided to battle on a ground where the behemoth from Seattle could not compete: In the field of elegant design. Hawkins' focus was to make the product as beautiful as possible, and they hired acclaimed design firm IDEO to design the Palm IV. Not only was it easy on the eyes and easy to use, but it was the first consumer product with a lithium battery, and the first to use glue, rather than screws, for seamless closure.
  - Ballmer, Steven Anthony, The Start-Up During Economic Crisis, 2009-05-06; 2254; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Critical screening, careful thought processes, and cash-conscience customers don't signal the end of the start-up, says Microsoft CEO Ballmer, Steve. But they do indicate that only the best and most solid ideas will receive the funding and other resources to bring them to fruition. As we reflect upon the economic crisis of 2008/2009, Ballmer describes entrepreneurial opportunities as "less frothy", but indicates his optimism for great solutions coming to market.
  - Ballmer, Steven Anthony, The Slow Incubation of Disruptive Technologies, 2009-05-06; 2255; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Important ideas aren't born overnight, stresses Microsoft CEO Ballmer, Steve. They can take up to a decade or more to truly come to light. Examples of projects worth the wait include Windows, SQL databases, and the Google search engine. Hard work, he promises, will lead a revolution in the end.
  - Ballmer, Steven Anthony, Emerging Trends in the Future of Technology, 2009-05-06; 2256; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Have all of the great technology companies already been created? Not even close, insists Ballmer, Steve, Microsoft's CEO. The only thing for certain in the future of technology is its dynamism, and that the names and the players are always changing. Ballmer points to smart displays and better human-computer interaction as future areas of exploration. He credits software with having impact on the future of energy, environmental science, and other fields.
  - Ballmer, Steven Anthony, Microsoft's Research and Development, 2009-05-06; 2257; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Touch, voice, natural language input, smart hardware, and new platforms: Ballmer, Steve, Microsoft CEO, outlines the company's $9 million path of product research for 2009. Overall, he states that the company is optimistic for what can be created in the future. In this clip, he talks about the company's strong need to create and innovate just like a start-up - despite the fact that they're one of the largest names in the industry.
  - Ballmer, Steven Anthony, The Interplay of Venture Capital and Innovation, 2009-05-06; 2258; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    More venture capital means more companies, but it does not necessarily mean more innovation, says Ballmer, Steve, CEO of Microsoft. And on that same token, the restrictions in financing that resulted from the financial crisis of 2008/2009 will not necessarily quash the future of innovation, either. Ballmer believes that the best ideas in technology - true next steps - will come to light despite even amidst the most inhospitable market conditions.
  - Ballmer, Steven Anthony, Balance and Tension in Company Culture, 2009-05-06; 2259; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Ballmer, Steve, Microsoft's CEO, considers the importance of balance and the tension between symbiotic and opposing forces in the enterprise. In this clip, he takes a philosophical perspective on company culture, including the interplay of far-reaching patience and meeting short-term goals, and teetering between a passion for technology and a passion for the customer.
  - Ballmer, Steven Anthony, The Launch of Ballmer's Microsoft Career, 2009-05-06; 2260; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Ballmer, Steve had always envisioned himself to be a big company guy - but he never dreamed that he would have to grow the company from the ground up. In this amusing anecdote on the roots of Microsoft's salad days, the company CEO recalls how he he took on the business responsibilities at the fledgeling start-up. At Bill Gates' invitation, Ballmer took on a low-risk summer job, never dreaming that it would result in one of the largest industry players enduring for over three decades.
  - Ballmer, Steven Anthony, Choosing the Right Projects, 2009-05-06; 2261; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Despite Microsoft's size and market dominance, CEO Ballmer, Steve considers himself to be a "mini venture capitalist" in a sea of bright ideas and new market possibilities. Working with the best and the brightest, his is the final word on tough decisions regarding which ideas and projects receive funding and other in-house resources from the company's limited pool. New products come and go with varying success, but by staying focused on core-competancies and core-strategies, says Ballmer, the right decisions will always come to light.
  - Ballmer, Steven Anthony, Applying Education to On-the-Job Experience, 2009-05-06; 2262; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    After just one year at Stanford's business school before joining Microsoft, Ballmer, Steve reflects upon the knowledge and courses that were most valuable to him in the real world. He recalls that it came in handy to read a balance sheet and understand the basics of cost accounting. Courses of study that were particularly helpful include business policy and management of arts organizations, which, he says, is more akin to managing engineers and scientists than one would think. STVP's Seelig, Tina also asks Ballmer to reflect upon what he wishes he'd learned. In retrospect, if he could retrace his steps in academia, his desire would be to take more computer science classes.
  - Westly, Steve, Historical and Global Change Through Clean Technology, 2009-05-20; 2263; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    With the long-term health of the planet at risk and the history of alternative energies in the making, Westly, Steve, former CFO for the state of California and founder of VC firm The Westly Group, challenges students and entrepreneurs to leave their hand print on the changing shape of the world. He cites the example of great explorers like Magellan and Columbus who broadly reached beyond boundaries never thought capable of being broken. Dependance on oil has these same challenges. He asks the audience, "What new things are you going to discover?"
  - Westly, Steve, Energy Reform and Cap and Trade, 2009-05-20; 2264; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Business leaders put pressure on elected officials, and they should be vying for a worldwide mandate on energy reduction, cleaner building materials, and the adoption of Japanese and European energy standards that are some of the most stringent in the world. Westly, Steve, Founder of The Westly Group and former CFO of California, calls for global reform and the adoption of carbon cap and trade, stating that these real solutions to help propel the planet aren't any more difficult to implement or use than EBay.
  - Westly, Steve, Clean Tech's Impact on Recessionary Times, 2009-05-20; 2265; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    When orders for Tesla cars outshine orders for the GM Saturn, Westly, Steve takes this as a sign that clean technologies are going to help lift America from the recession of 2008/2009. He points to other indicators, such as that abundance of clean tech company IPO's, that will also help add new stems and leaves to the economy. As an aside, he also parallels the difference between US start-ups, enabled by the safety net of a VC-backed ecosystem, and their Chinese counterparts, who are forced to be profitable immediately or shutter.
  - Seelig, Tina Lynn, The Art of Teaching Entrepreneurship and Innovation (Entire Talk), 2009-05-27; 2266; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Stanford Technology Ventures Program's Executive Director Seelig, Tina shares rich insights in creative thinking and the entrepreneurial mindset. Her talk, based on her 2009 book, What I Wish I Knew When I Was 20, cites numerous classroom successes of applied problem-solving and the lessons of failure.
  - Seelig, Tina Lynn, Teaching Creativity and Entrepreneurship, 2009-05-27; 2267; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Seelig, Tina, Executive Director of Stanford Technology Ventures Program, speaks about the lesson that is the crux of entrepreneurship: All problems are opportunities, and the larger the problem, the grander the opportunity. Furthermore, she talks about the challenges that arise in the methods for teaching these concepts, and the necessity to get people out of their comfort zone in order to encourage creative problem-solving. This clip also includes a video quote from Khosla, Vinod.
  - Seelig, Tina Lynn, Classroom Experiments in Entrepreneurship, 2009-05-27; 2268; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    If you had five dollars and two hours, what would you do to make as much money as possible? In this clip, STVP Executive Director Seelig, Tina recalls a classroom exercise in creative thinking and entrepreneurship that posed this quandry to student teams. The results were manifold and varied, often taking advantage of ly needed services, niche markets, and valuable time. These in-class experiments contain many valuable lessons on creative thinking in the start-up realm, including skills, ideas, and innovation as assets that always lend value.
  - Seelig, Tina Lynn, Turning Lemonade Into Helicopters, 2009-05-27; 2269; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Solving problems is an important aspect of entrepreneurship, but it's not the entire solution. Aspiring students also need to learn how to make their own good luck, says STVP Executive Director Seelig, Tina. Hard work is imperative, but it doesn't always mean a fortunate outcome. It takes optimism, an open mind, shrewd networking skills, and the ability to find the veiled "million dollars in the room." Seelig cites a personal anecdote where, through perseverance and curiosity, she turned an encounter with a stranger over frozen lemonade in a grocery store into a long-lasting relationship and a helicopter ride to a private ski resort overseas.
  - Seelig, Tina Lynn, Fail Fast and Frequently, 2009-05-27; 2270; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    What's the secret sauce of Silicon Valley? Failure, reports Seelig, Tina, Executive Director of the Stanford Technology Ventures Program. To develop more successes, she urges, entrepreneurs have got to take a risk, and this is the notion behind every deal in the entire ecosystem. Venture capitalists fund risk and, by association, failure, in order to find the "hits" in the haystack. Failure is a perfectly acceptable part of the entrepreneurial process, provided that the smart entrepreneur learns from their errors along the way.
  - Seelig, Tina Lynn, Don't Wait to be Anointed, 2009-05-27; 2271; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Don't think of a job as just getting a desk and a job description. Seelig, Tina, Executive Director of Stanford Technology Ventures Program, points out that landing a job means getting a key to the building. And what that key unlocks is entirely up to you. The endless possibilities of creating work, new projects, and developing ideas that cater to your passions are available to any employee in any office. Seelig urges entrepreneurial thinking in the workplace, and tells students that they should build the ladder below themselves, rather than waiting for someone else to put it before them.
  - Li, Yanhong, 1968-, Opportunities in China at the Age of Innovation, 2009-09-23; 2280; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    With no business model and a company that was barely solvent, Baidu CEO Li, Robin quickly realized that his customer base didn't want to buy the best technology; only the cheapest. The entire strategy of his company needed to change, and he revamped his enterprise from a back-end search utility to a front-end, consumer-focused provider. Since making this change in 2001, Baidu has gone on to become one of the most successful online search tools on the planet.
  - Li, Yanhong, 1968-, Sharpening Focus in the Face of Market Turmoil, 2009-09-23; 2281; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Focusing on technology, operations, and the user experience, Li, Robin, CEO of Chinese search engine Baidu, took a pragmatic approach and recalls how he took on the role of project manager for the company for nearly a year. Focusing on nothing but search services, the company avvoided the market crash of 2000/2001 and resisted the trends in online development, and instead continued to play to the company's best strengths.
  - Li, Yanhong, 1968-, Shedding Light on the "Dark" Web, 2009-09-23; 2282; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    In an effort to index the 99 percent of the "dark" web - that is, the vast majority of web pages unreachable by most search tools - Li, Robin, CEO of China's Baidu, launched a product called Aladdin. The goal of the open interface is to allow for and encourage user content submission, and to provide the site's users with a deeper, unbridled search capability.
  - Li, Yanhong, 1968-, The Future of Box Computing, 2009-09-23; 2283; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Described as not just a function of search, but a "vision for our future", the CEO of Baidu, Li, Robin, talks about the continuing emergence of the "magic" search box as the primary tool for browserless, consolidated information gathering. He also discusses at length how search terms have evolved - no longer just subject queries, but users hunting for everything from weather and movie time information, arithmetic solutions, and even dating help. From his stance, the empty box awaiting information is the simplest, easiest-to-learn computing platform, operating independently of location, operating system, or application.
  - Li, Yanhong, 1968-, China's Labor Demands in Computer Science, 2009-09-23; 2284; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    More than 700,000 computer science-related engineering students graduate each year in China, but few from this labor pool have the experience necessary to help an innovative company grow, says Li, Robin, CEO of search engine Baidu. And, he points out, the management opportunities on a global scale are tremendous. That said, he and his company also outline the qualities that they seek in incoming talent - including a readiness to learn, a political and hassle-free outlook, and supreme reliability.
  - Li, Yanhong, 1968-, Critical Early Decisions with Long Lasting Results, 2009-09-23; 2285; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    The pivotal points that changed the direction of Baidu's emergence, says its CEO Li, Robin, include fewer extravagant expenditures (and planning for six months of capital to last for over a year), a switch from a back-end to a consumer-oriented interface, and a conscious decision to outshine the competition. In addition, Li recalls the ten months he spent micromanaging the engineering team to quickly turnaround the best quality technology the team could muster. He credits all of these early-term risks with the long-term sustainability of the enterprise.
  - Li, Yanhong, 1968-, How North American Search Companies Faltered in China, 2009-09-23; 2286; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    What is it that American search companies have failed to understand in China? Baidu's CEO Li, Robin asserts numerous reasons that foreign-based search tools underestimated the growth of China's online content in the 1990's and early 2000's. He first points out that the capabilities of Google and Yahoo! overseas did not match China's tremendous scale of content growth. In addition, North American companies underestimated the fierce competition and entrepreneurial spirit of the Chinese. And many Internet companies coming to China did not plan for the long-term investment necessary to fully mesh with the market.
  - Li, Yanhong, 1968-, The Development of China's Silicon Valley, 2009-09-23; 2287; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    It's not a million dollar question. It's a trillion dollar question, says Li, Robin, CEO of Baidu, on the emergence of a Silicon Valley entrepreneurial ecosystem in China. Though the country's economy is enormous, much of it is based on cheap labor and inexpensive manufacturing. Many in China, particularly those in government, says Li, are very interested in developing the country's potential, but the task of replicating that kind of innovation has many roadblocks in its path.
  - Jurvetson, Steve, Innovation in a Disruptive Environment (Entire Talk), 2009-10-07; 2288; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Jurvetson, Steve, partner at Draper Fisher Jurvetson, offers perspective on the market opportunities in innovation and technology. Topics discussed include the necessity for utter market disruption, interdisciplinary solutions, and advice for those interested in working in the venture capital arena.
  - Ries, Eric, The Lean Startup: Debunking Myths of Entrepreneurship, 2009-09-30; 2289; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    A startup is not a "doll house" version of a larger enterprise. It's a human institution trying to start something new under extreme conditions of uncertainty, says author Ries, Eric. It's not that some founders have better ideas than others, and this is what dictates success. What differentiates a successfully launched enterprise is one who can unearth the best ideas under duress - those who can find "the pivot"- the point of reinvention when they realize that their original ideas need retooling. And, more critically, that they can find their market before they run out of money.
  - Ries, Eric, Achieving Grandiose Failure, 2009-09-30; 2290; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    After five years of product build-out and $40 million of capital, author Ries, Eric shares his personal story of monumental startup failure. The important distinction that he draws is not that his company failed to execute. To the contrary, all went strictly to plan, hiring the best talent, releasing a well-tested application, and garnering ample media and user attention. But the fledgling enterprise was a monumental disaster because of "shadow beliefs" - a uniformly-held series of ideas the company never discussed or articulated. Among them, they believed that they knew what customers wanted, they erroneously believed they could predict the future, and they took solace in the idea that plan advancement equals measurable progress.
  - Ries, Eric, Harnessing the Power of Early Adopters, 2009-09-30; 2291; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    After a very hi-profile startup failure, author Ries, Eric and other co-founders launched a second startup product in just six months - with technically hazardous results. Rather than investing the resources necessary to craft quality software, they decided to switch tactics and release a buggy version quickly to determine if the product could find a market. Ries found that early adopters - often more visionary than the company founders - were a huge asset in streamlining product development. Working with them from the very early stages allowed for a better-engineered product and broader mainstream market success. Ries offers suggestion on how to find these initial users; often through search engine marketing and Google AdWords, StumbleUpon campaigns, and creative Facebook ads.
  - Ries, Eric, Agile Vs. Waterfall Product Engineering, 2009-09-30; 2292; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Author and entrepreneur Ries, Eric unpacks the difference between waterfall and agile product development theories, and outlines when each are best employed. Waterfall - the linear path of product build-out - is best used when the problem and its solutions are well-understood. However, its hazard is that it can also lead to tremendous investment without guarantee of its success. Agile development, on the other hand, is a less-risky model of what can happen when the product changes with frequent user feedback and minimal waste. Without an authoritative solution clearly in sight, which is often the case of the startup, agile programming allows the growing enterprise to build-out quickly and correct itself often.
  - Ries, Eric, Building a Product Nobody Wants, 2009-09-30; 2293; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    The largest source of waste in the startup, says author and entrepreneur Ries, Eric, is building a product that no one will find useful. This is not a technical error, but rather a tactical one. Find out early if your product has merit by developing two teams in-house: One that works on problems uncovering who the customer is and what problems they are trying to solve, and one that focuses solely on the solutions for the current product hypothesis.
  - Ries, Eric, An Argument for Continuous Deployment, 2009-09-30; 2294; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)